<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-21T02:52:09+00:00</updated><id>https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/feed.xml</id><title type="html">wocqcm2</title><subtitle>An engaging 1-3 sentence description of your lab.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Lab Member Publishes Research on Support Networks and Psychological Well-Being</title><link href="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2025/03/25/qin-meng-support-network-research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lab Member Publishes Research on Support Networks and Psychological Well-Being" /><published>2025-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-21T02:48:44+00:00</updated><id>https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2025/03/25/qin-meng-support-network-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2025/03/25/qin-meng-support-network-research.html"><![CDATA[<p>Jiaqi Qin, under Professor Meng’s guidance, published research on support network typology and psychological well-being in young adults. The study appears in Health Communication journal. This research identifies patterns of social support structures and their impact on mental health outcomes.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="support-network-typology-and-psychological-well-being-among-young-adults">Support Network Typology and Psychological Well-Being Among Young Adults</h2>

<p>The Communication and Computation Lab is pleased to announce that lab member Jiaqi Qin, working under the mentorship of Professor Jingbo Meng, has published a research article in Health Communication. The article, titled “Support Network Typology and Psychological Well-Being Among Young Adults,” was published online on March 25, 2025.</p>

<p>This study investigates how different types of support networks influence psychological well-being among young adults. The research identifies distinct patterns of social support structures and examines their relationship with various mental health outcomes. By understanding these patterns, the researchers aim to develop more effective support interventions for young adults experiencing psychological distress.</p>

<p>The findings highlight the importance of considering network structure, not just the presence of support, when assessing psychological well-being. This research builds on Professor Meng’s ongoing work on social networks and support communication, further establishing the lab’s expertise in this important area of health communication research.</p>

<p>The article can be accessed at: <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10410236.2025.2480684">Support Network Typology and Psychological Well-Being Among Young Adults</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jiaqi Qin, under Professor Meng’s guidance, published research on support network typology and psychological well-being in young adults. The study appears in Health Communication journal. This research identifies patterns of social support structures and their impact on mental health outcomes.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news03-25-2025.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news03-25-2025.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Professor Meng Participates in Discussion on AI Companion Bots for Teens</title><link href="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2025/02/07/ai-companion-bots-teens.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Professor Meng Participates in Discussion on AI Companion Bots for Teens" /><published>2025-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-21T02:48:44+00:00</updated><id>https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2025/02/07/ai-companion-bots-teens</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2025/02/07/ai-companion-bots-teens.html"><![CDATA[<p>Professor Jingbo Meng from Ohio State University participated in a discussion about AI companion bots for teenagers. She shared insights from her research on social networks and chatbots, highlighting the difference between artificial and human empathy. Professor Meng emphasized the need for balancing AI interactions with human connections.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="ai-companion-bots-benefits-and-risks-for-teenagers">AI Companion Bots: Benefits and Risks for Teenagers</h2>

<p>In recent research examining AI companions and their effects on psychological health, Professor Jingbo Meng from Ohio State University’s School of Communication has found important distinctions between machine and human interaction patterns.</p>

<p>“Competent communication from a chatbot doesn’t translate to psychological well-being,” notes Professor Meng, whose research focuses on social networks, chatbots, and artificial intelligence systems.</p>

<p>Her studies indicate that users might not consciously recognize differences when interacting with AI versus humans, yet when people are aware they’re communicating with an actual caring person, there’s a measurable reduction in psychological distress. This finding has significant implications as AI companion apps like Replika, Character.AI, and Snapchat’s My AI gain popularity among teenagers.</p>

<p>Professor Meng emphasizes the importance of balancing technology with human connection: “There’s a need to better integrate human and AI interactions—so that AI doesn’t replace human contact.” She also advocates for improved digital literacy education in schools to help young people navigate these emerging technologies.</p>

<p>The research contributes to a growing body of knowledge about AI companions, which experts note can provide emotional support but also pose risks including dependency, privacy concerns, and potentially harmful advice.</p>

<p><a href="https://cacm.acm.org/news/will-ai-companion-bots-be-beneficial-for-teens/">Read the full article on ACM.org</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Professor Jingbo Meng from Ohio State University participated in a discussion about AI companion bots for teenagers. She shared insights from her research on social networks and chatbots, highlighting the difference between artificial and human empathy. Professor Meng emphasized the need for balancing AI interactions with human connections.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news02-07-2025.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news02-07-2025.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Professor Meng Presents on AI Chatbots in Health Communication at UW-Madison</title><link href="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2024/04/10/professor-meng-lecture-ai-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Professor Meng Presents on AI Chatbots in Health Communication at UW-Madison" /><published>2024-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-21T02:48:44+00:00</updated><id>https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2024/04/10/professor-meng-lecture-ai-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2024/04/10/professor-meng-lecture-ai-health.html"><![CDATA[<p>Professor Jingbo Meng from Ohio State University presented research on AI chatbots for mental health support at UW-Madison’s spring colloquium. She examined whether AI companions can provide comparable outcomes to human mental health professionals. Her findings suggest that while AI chatbots can be helpful, they lack the immediate connection established by human care providers.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="ai-chatbots-for-health-support-research-insights-from-professor-meng">AI Chatbots for Health Support: Research Insights from Professor Meng</h2>

<p>On April 10, 2024, Professor Jingbo Meng from Ohio State University’s School of Communication presented her research on AI chatbots in health communication at UW-Madison’s Life Sciences Communication spring colloquium. Her talk addressed a critical question: “Is it true that AI chatbots provide comparable health outcomes to mental health professionals?”</p>

<p>Professor Meng’s research examined various AI mental health applications, including Woebot (a rule-based chatbot informed by cognitive behavioral therapy) and Wysa (an anonymous mental health support tool). One key benefit she highlighted was users’ ability to seek help without fear of judgment or burdening friends and family.</p>

<p>“AI chatbots can be helpful. We see that participants feel supported when talking to chatbots, which leads to a reduction in stress and worry,” noted Professor Meng. However, she clarified an important distinction: “A well-performing chatbot can be equivalent to a support provider, but only in terms of a participant’s evaluation of them. With a human provider, if they show care about you, there is an immediate effect. But with AI chatbots, you don’t have that.”</p>

<p>Her research also addressed gaps in online support communities. In studying mental health forums on Reddit, Professor Meng found that many people seeking help receive no responses. This highlighted a potential role for AI: “Online support group members may need help themselves, and may not have the time or energy to help others. In this situation, is it appropriate to use AI chatbots to support them? AI chatbots seem to be promising, but not quite there yet.”</p>

<p>An innovative aspect of Professor Meng’s work explores how human volunteers in online support communities use AI tools like ChatGPT. Some use it as an information search tool, while others employ it as a writing assistant. Interestingly, messages generated by AI or through human-AI collaboration were perceived as more helpful and authentic compared to human-only messages.</p>

<p>“We found that age was negatively associated with willingness to use ChatGPT, but AI experience was a positive predictor,” Professor Meng explained. Her research suggests that in online support communities, “AI chatbots may help augment humans’ ability to communicate support.”</p>

<p><strong>Original Source</strong>: <a href="https://x.com/UW_LSC/status/1778099595827872071">UW-Madison LSC Twitter Thread</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Professor Jingbo Meng from Ohio State University presented research on AI chatbots for mental health support at UW-Madison’s spring colloquium. She examined whether AI companions can provide comparable outcomes to human mental health professionals. Her findings suggest that while AI chatbots can be helpful, they lack the immediate connection established by human care providers.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news04-10-2024.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news04-10-2024.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Professor Meng’s Talk on Social Support in the Digital Age</title><link href="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2023/07/15/meng-digital-social-support-talk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Professor Meng’s Talk on Social Support in the Digital Age" /><published>2023-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-21T02:48:44+00:00</updated><id>https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2023/07/15/meng-digital-social-support-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/2023/07/15/meng-digital-social-support-talk.html"><![CDATA[<p>Professor Jingbo Meng delivered a talk at Seoul National University on “Social Support in the Digital Age: Social Network and Artificial Intelligence.” She shared research on the structural model of online social support and experimental findings on using artificial intelligence to communicate social support. The lecture explored how technology influences social support systems and compared human-machine interactions with interpersonal interactions.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/L919QMU4i8E" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Professor Jingbo Meng delivered a talk at Seoul National University on “Social Support in the Digital Age: Social Network and Artificial Intelligence.” She shared research on the structural model of online social support and experimental findings on using artificial intelligence to communicate social support. The lecture explored how technology influences social support systems and compared human-machine interactions with interpersonal interactions.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news07-15-2022.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://wocqcm2.github.io/Communication-and-Computation-Lab/images/news/news07-15-2022.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>